Soviet Union Evangelical Lutheran Subject Files, Inclusive: 1953-2006, undated, Bulk: 1975-1989
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society
Soviet Union Evangelical Lutheran Subject Files
Inclusive: 1953-2006, undated, Bulk: 1975-1989
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society http://www.baylor.edu/kestoncenter/
35
The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society
2 A4 document boxes
The Soviet Union Evangelical Lutheran Subject Files contain a variety of materials on the persecution of and discrimination against members of the Evangelical Lutheran Church in the Soviet Union and post-Soviet Russia.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Keston College, originally founded in 1969 as the Center for the Study of Religion and Communism with the named changed to Keston College in 1974, collected and publicized details about religious persecution behind the Iron Curtain, becoming “the voice of the voiceless.” After the collapse of communism in the 1990s, Keston College moved to Oxford and downsized due to decreased funding. The name eventually changed to Keston Institute. In 2007, the Institute transferred the Keston Archive and Library to the newly created Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society at Baylor University.
Keston collected, verified, translated, and disseminated information received from believers in the Soviet Union, Poland, Romania, Czechoslovakia, Hungary, Yugoslavia, Bulgaria and other communist countries. The Keston Archive and Library housed numerous letters, petitions, reports and underground publications (Samizdat) from believers of various denominations along with officially published books and periodicals.
The Keston Center collected and maintained records related to Evangelical Lutherans in the Soviet Union from the early 1950s through the early 2000s. The collection contains records that not only speak to the experiences of Evangelical Lutherans, both regionally and individually, but also includes sources that detail the background of how German Evangelical Lutherans first arrived in the Soviet Union.
Lutheran beliefs first spread to the Baltic region, including Finland, Estonia, and Latvia, in the 16th century. About 200 years later in the 1760s, a large group of Germans settled in the Volga region of Russia through an immigration policy instituted by Catherine the Great. Of those with a religious background who were a part of the process, 75% were Lutheran. Thus, a majority of the Lutherans in the Soviet Union sprang these families. The area became so tied to the German population that it became known as a “German colony” or “the Volga German Republic.” Although, some sources state that the offspring of these immigrants were deported as early as the 1930s, most remained in the region until 1941, when Stalin exiled them to Siberia and Central Asia. Eventually, a large group of the remaining Volga Germans settled in Kazakhstan while others spread throughout the USSR. The influential presence of these Lutherans in Kazakhstan can be seen in the registration of the first USSR German Lutheran church there in 1957.
By the 1960s, the largest Soviet Lutheran population was contained within the Baltic region. In 1989, the primary Christian denomination in Latvia was Lutheran. Latvia’s rise to becoming more of the center of the Evangelical Lutherans in the Soviet Union was also evidenced by the Rebirth and Renewal Movement in the late 1980s.
During the latter half of the 20th century, church life for Evangelical Lutherans in the Soviet Union was difficult. Churches had to be registered, and pastors were required to be licensed. Overall, the government often controlled and persecuted the churches. Frequently, pastors’ licenses were revoked, and they were watched by the Council for Religious Affairs. Some were arrested, and others were admitted to psychiatric hospitals. Despite the injustices, some more positive situations occurred, such as in the late 1980s when Latvian public schools could teach religion as an optional course.
Scope and Content
The Soviet Union Evangelical Lutheran Subject Files contain abstracts, newspaper articles, newspaper clippings, Keston College news reports, bibliographic references, and Glaube in Der 2. Welt publications. The dates span 1953 to 2006, with the bulk from 1975-1989. The most common subjects include, but are not limited to, church sizes, Lutheran World Federation (LWF), Germans on the Volga, atheist propaganda, KGB persecution, general persecution, individual leaders of Soviet Lutheran churches, Rebirth and Renewal Movement, Church and State relations, and Baltic States (Estonia, Latvia, Lithuania) experiences. The most prominent individuals listed within the collection are Modris Plate, Vello Salum, Bishop Harald Kalnins, Archbishop Edgar Hark, Bishop Harri Motsnik, Ivars Grabans, and Semyon Gluzman.
Arrangement
The Keston Center received the Soviet Union Evangelical Lutheran Subject Files arranged by topic. This original filing system has been preserved. The individual sources within each file have been organized by date.
The Soviet Union Evangelical Lutheran Subject Files are arranged into two series: I. General and II. Samizdat.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to the Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 35.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
Keston College -- Archives.; Keston Institute -- Archives.; Lutheran World Federation.
Places
Asia, Central -- Religion -- 20th century.; Siberia (Russia) -- Religion.
Subjects
Church and state -- Lutheran Church.; Church and state -- Soviet Union.; Communism and Christianity -- Soviet Union.; Dissenters -- Soviet Union.; Germans -- Soviet Union.; Human rights -- Soviet Union.; Lutheran Church -- Soviet Union.; Persecution -- Soviet Union.; Political prisoners -- Abuse of -- Soviet Union.; Political prisoners -- Soviet Union.
Genres
Abstracts.; Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Publications.; References.
- General, 1953-2006; 1
  Administrative Information
  Biography/Profile
  This series focuses on church and state relations; persecution; and individual church, regional church, and individual clergy experiences.
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church. General (1 of 6), 1953-1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church. General (2 of 6), 1973-1979, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church. General (3 of 6), 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church. General (4 of 6), 1982-2000 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church. General (5 of 6), 1971 November (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church. General (6 of 6), undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church. History. General, 1963-1995, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church. History. Lutherans on the Volga, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church. History. Soviet Period, 1980-1985 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church. Individual Believers, 1975-1979, 1983 August, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church Administration, 1977 March, 1989 January-February (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church. List of Churches, 1977 March (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Individual Evangelical Lutheran Churches, 1975-1997, 2006, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church. Lutheran World Federation, 1991, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church of Latvia, 1983 July, 1989 April (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church — State Relations (1 of 2), 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church — State Relations (2 of 2), 1979, 1988 March, 1997 October, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church. Restoration of Churches, 1978-1992 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church. Registration of Churches, 1975-1988 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Oppressive Practices against Evangelical Lutheran Church. General, 1973-1986 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Oppressive Practices against Evangelical Lutheran Church. Imprisonment, 1977-1986, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Oppressive Practices against Evangelical Lutheran Church. State Interference in Church Affairs, 1978 February (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Oppressive Practices against Evangelical Lutheran Church. Legal Disabilities, Refusal of Registration, and Closure of Churches, 1978 March, 1989 January (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Oppressive Practices against Evangelical Lutheran Church. State Interference in Parish Level Administration and Parish Life, 1987 May (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Oppressive Practices against Evangelical Lutheran Church. State Interference in the Affairs of Clergy and Hierarchy, 1984 March, 1987 April-November (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Oppressive Practices against Evangelical Lutheran Church. State Expropriation, Desecration, or Demolition of Church Buildings, 1979-1981 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Oppressive Practices against Evangelical Lutheran Church. Psychiatric Abuse, 1981-1988 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Oppressive Practices against Evangelical Lutheran Church. Attacks in Media, 1977 May, 1987 July (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church Life. General, 1976-1988, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Church Life, Evangelical Lutheran Church in Estonia, 1982-1986 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church in Latvia, 1981 August, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church in Lithuania, 1983-1985 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church in Siberia, 1976 December, 1990 April, 1997 October, 2001 September (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church in Central Asia, 1978-1991, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church Life. Festivals and Anniversaries, 1968-1992 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church Life. Services and Rituals, 1991 December (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church Life. Preaching, Evangelism, and Conversions, 1976, 1979 April (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church. Parish Life, 1977-1982 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church Life. Defection from Faith, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church Life. Official Church Publications, 1982 February (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church Life. Revival, Charismatic Renewal, 1988 November, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church Life. Philanthropy, 2003 March (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church Clergy and Priesthood. General, 1980-1988 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church Hierarchy, 1976 March, 1981 August (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church Clergy and Priesthood. Ordination, Election, and Retirement, 1977-1992 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church. Individual Clergy. General, 1972-1991, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church. Individual Clergy. Archbishop Edgar Hark, 1976-1982, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church. Individual Clergy. Bishop Harald Kalnins, 1986-1989, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church. Individual Clergy. Bishop Harri Motsnik, 1985-1987 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church International Relations. Western Reactions, Protests, and Appeals, 1977 May-June, 1980 August, 1988 November (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church International Relations. Delegations from SU Visit Abroad, 1979 November (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church International Relations. Visits from Foreign Delegations, 1976-1988, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church. Religious Activities Disapproved by the State. General, 1976 December, 1981 October (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church. Christian Movement “Rebirth and Renewal”, 1987 April-November (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church. Criticism of Church Policies by Believers, 1987 September (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church. Emigration on Religious Grounds, 1971-1978, 1983 August, 1990 August, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church. Theological Education, 1976-1999 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church. Religious Education of Children, 1988 November-December (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church. Statistics, 1967-1986 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church. Relations with Fellow Believers. General, 1977 July (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church. Relations with Fellow Believers. Finland, 1976 October, 1985 November, 2003 March (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church. Relations with Fellow Believers. East Germany and West Germany, 1979-1989 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church. Relations with Fellow Believers. LWF, 1980-1989, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church. Relations with Fellow Believers. Evangelical Lutheran Diaspora, 1978-1980 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church. Relations with Fellow Believers. Evangelical Lutheran Latvian Church in Exile, 1988 April (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church. Ecumenical Relations with Other Denominations, 1975 October, 1979 April (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church. Religion and National Identity, 1980 January, 1981 July, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church. Pronouncements on Secular Affairs, 1988 February-July (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church. Christian Socialists. Religious and Secular Political Movements, 1979 April, 1989 January (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church. Music, 1981-1988 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church Architecture. Restoration, 1976 April (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church. Bible, 1971-1987 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church. Children and Youth, 1976-1977, 1986 August, undated (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church. Late Soviet and Post-Soviet Period. Western Press Clippings, 1990-1991, 1993 February (Box 2, Folder 53)
- Samizdat, 1977-1982; 2
  This series focuses primarily on church and state relations.
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church. Individual Members. Grabans, Ivars, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church. Individual Clergy. Bishop Harri Motsnik, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Church. Religion and National Identity, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 56)